Valerie Phillip

Product Steward/Regulatory Specialist

Elkins Park, PA - Email me on Indeed: indeed.com/r/Valerie-Phillip/2f817087b8c80585

A senior Product Steward and Regulatory Specialist with over 20 years of experience supporting the chemicals industry. Knowledgeable in emerging technical and regulatory issues that impact the risk and liability of the organization. Skilled in risk management to support compliance obligations and integrate product stewardship with business process management. A strong and flexible team player with the ability and desire to meet the needs of internal and external customers.

Willing to relocate: Anywhere

Authorized to work in the US for any employer

WORK EXPERIENCE

Senior Product Steward/Regulatory Specialist, Dow Microbial Control

THE DOW CHEMICAL COMPANY (Former Rohm and Haas Company) - 2008 to 2015

Managed biocide product regulatory compliance process including registrations from the US Environmental Protection Agency (EPA) regulated under the Federal Insecticide Fungicide Rodenticide Act (FIFRA), including Technical Grade Active Ingredients (TGAI), Manufacturing Use Products (MUP), End Use Products (EUP) and Alternate Formulations. Proficient in use of SAP for process management.

- * Successfully implemented GHS (Globally Harmonized Systems) bringing biocide Material Safety Data Sheets (MSDS) into compliance
- * Successfully implemented EPA's "Container and Containment" regulation bringing regulated labels into compliance
- * Managed Distributor and Supplemental Registrations, including the set-up of 11 alternate formulations for both US and Canada for a new Joint Venture that increased customer satisfaction
- * Delivered on business critical registration of new form of biocide(tablets) for Water Treatment market that resulted in 2 new MUP's and 4 new EUP's which expanded product base for global customers
- * Trained both internal and external customers on Product Safety and Regulatory Compliance to ensure awareness of critical issues that could impact product marketing

Product Steward/Regulatory Specialist, Consumer and Industrial Specialties

Rohm and Haas Company - 2000 to 2008

Obtained US EPA registrations for biocide products regulated under FIFRA and acquiring state registrations for the marketing of those products.

- * Successfully converted biocide product labels to SAP
- * Successfully implemented EPA's "First Aid" regulation bringing regulated labels into compliance
- * Managed Distributor and Supplemental Registrations, including label review and approval of 250+ supplemental labels that ensured compliance with EPA's "First Aid" regulation
- * Managed State Registrations for biocide products, including Product Rationalization Project that resulted in reduced cost of \$100K+ in annual registration fees.
- * Acted as liaison between research and business unit for registration support data

Product Safety and Hazard Communication Specialist, Product Integrity

Rohm and Haas Company - 1992 to 2000

Authored Material Safety Data Sheets (MSDS) for company's Performance Chemicals.

- * Provided regulatory analysis for worldwide inventory status for product compliance
- * Maintained compositional database for performance chemicals
- * Worked with hazardous communication core team to manage and distribute workload
- * Successfully implemented the ANSI Standard 16 section MSDS governed by OSHA (Occupational Safety and Health Administration) to ensure compliance for Performance materials

Technical Assistant, Separation Technologies

Rohm and Haas Company - 1987 to 1992

Synthesized Polymer Resins for various vendor applications, analyzed physical properties of produced resin, presented scientific data for update and new applications to management. Supervised laboratory chemicals and equipment, trained student co-ops and employees on equipment safety, maintained resin inventory and tracked waste disposal.

Technical Assistant, Monomers Research

Rohm and Haas Company - 1981 to 1987

Synthesized Acrylic Monomers and Acrylates used as based materials in consumer products, synthesized and isolated monomer components in an inert atmospheric container, performed analytical sampling, data tabulation and interpretation for presentation to management. Operated and maintained 24 hr. continuous distillation unit.

EDUCATION

B.A. in Chemistry and Biology

Arcadia University (former Beaver College) - Glenside, PA

ACS(American Chemical Society) Accreditation

LaSalle University - Philadelphia, PA

SKILLS

SAP, Microsoft Word, Excel and Power Point

LINKS

http://www.linkedin.com/in/valphillip

ADDITIONAL INFORMATION

CORE COMPETENCIES

- * Project Management * Safety Planning & Implementation * Audit
- * Regulatory Compliance * Government Relations * Process Improvement
- * Environmental Compliance * Communication/Presentations * SAP

PROFESSIONAL AND VOLUNTEER ORGANIZATIONS

American Chemistry Council (ACC) Biocides Panel, 2000 - 2015

Society for Chemical Hazards Communication (SCHC), 1993 - 2000

National Organization for the Professional Advancement of Black Chemists and Chemical Engineers (NOBCCHE) 1993 - 2000

Actively involved in church organizations including Director of Pre-School Ministries, Facilitator for Divorce Care Ministries and Advisory Board Member for Senior Group, 2000- present